<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas-r5/fhir-single.xsd">

    <head>
        <style>
            table, th, td {
                border: 0.5px solid grey;
                padding: 2px 5px;
            }
        </style>
    </head>

    <p>This Implementation Guide uses FHIR defined resources – Composition Resource, Questionnaire Resource,
    QuestionnaireResponse Resource, Patient Resource, PractitionerRole Resource, Practitioner Resource, Organization Resource, ServiceRequest Resource and Bundle Resource from
    FHIR R4. For details on HL7 FHIR R4 see <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/r4">http://hl7.org/fhir/r4</a>.
    </p>
    <p>The Order &amp; Referral by Form (ORF) Implementation Guide describes how forms for eReferrals, requests for
        information (such as diagnostic imaging results, lab results, discharge reports etc.) can be defined, deployed and
        used in order to achieve a syntactical and semantically consistent cross enterprise information exchange.
    </p>
    <p>The Implementation Guide supports creation and domain wide deployment of forms for structured and coded information
        exchange as well as exchange of such forms for referral, orders etc. The Implementation Guide relies on FHIR e.g.
        the questionnaire resource. Because the Implementation Guide relies heavily on the FHIR Resources Questionnaire and
        QuestionnaireResponse, forms are addressed here as Questionnaires.
    </p>
    <p>This Implementation Guide is derived from the HL7 Structured Data Capture Implementation Guide, see 
        <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/">SDC IG (v2.7.0)</a> and uses the Swiss Core Profiles, see 
        <a href="https://fhir.ch/ig/ch-core/2.0.0/index.html">CH Core (v2.0.0)</a>.
    </p>

    <div markdown="1" class="stu-note">
      <a href="changelog.html">Significant Changes, Open and Closed Issues</a>
     </div>

    <p>
        <b>Download:</b>
        You can download this Implementation Guide in 
        <a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/display/FHIR/NPM+Package+Specification">NPM format</a> from 
        <a href="package.tgz">here</a>.
    </p>

    <a name="volume1"></a><h3>Volume 1 – Order &amp; Referral by Form (CH ORF) Implementation Guide</h3>
    <p>This Implementation Guide concerns directional information exchange between institutions such as requests for
        referral, requests for previous imaging results, requests for second opinions etc. as well as corresponding
        responses. Such request are often done – or could be done – by means of structured forms. The same may apply for
        responses or documents coming along in case the response consists of a particular payload (e.g. exam results).
        However, forms for these purposes are in general proprietary constructs and seldom suitable for further machine
        processing. Furthermore, such forms are more or less hard coded and concerned systems may not easily be updated for
        new use cases.
    </p>

    <p>The ORF Implementation Guide addresses two issues:
    </p>
    <ol>
        <li>It supports a scenario where an authority (e.g. health authority, expert panel etc.) defines a set of forms
        (here called Questionnaires) for well-defined use cases which then are deployed in a specific enterprise, domain
        etc. or even nationwide.</li>
        <li>New use cases or changes in use cases can easily be handled either by modification of existing Questionnaires or
        new ones. The Implementation Guide itself is agnostic to the nature of a particular Questionnaire and the ORF
        Implementation Guide puts only little limits on its definition.</li>
    </ol>
    <p>Vendors implementing the ORF Implementation Guide benefit of a high re-use potential. Applications which support the
    ORF Implementation Guide may be used for various settings of directional information exchange. The specific needs of
    a particular use case will be covered by a adequate design of the Questionnaire and the value sets being used.
    </p>
    <p>When writing the ORF Implementation Guide, the authors had the following use case in mind: A human fills in a
    Questionnaire for a particular request and sends this Questionnaire to a receiver. There, a human reads the
    Questionnaire with its content. A corresponding response will work in the same way. There is possibly some payload
    coming with the Questionnaire: A request may be accompanied by results of preceding exams (e.g. images, reports);
    the response may be a diagnostic result.
    </p>
    <p>The primary aim of the ORF Implementation Guide is to assure a consistent representation of Questionnaires at both –
    filler- and receiver – site. But there is the need for further machine processing: at filler site in terms of
    prepopulating attributes with content from other applications (e.g. demographic data of a patient) whereas the
    receiver may want to have the content of the form ready for further processing in his applications. Obviously the
    two aims – semantic interoperability and flexibility in the definition of Questionnaires – are contradictory. The
    ORF Implementation Guide addresses this problem by a mandatory set of generic elements and codes with
    defined meaning which are part of every Questionnaire in the ORF Implementation Guide. It is up to a SDC Form
    Designer to create Questionnaires with additional use case specific elements.
    </p>
    <p>There has been a discussion whether population of the resources such as Patient Resource, ServiceRequest Resource 
    etc. with the content of the QuestionnaireResponse Resource should be done by the order placer application or rather 
    by the order filler application. The argument for assigning the task to the order placer is a result of the following 
    consideration: the authors of a particular implementation guide  may decide to define a questionnaire and its rendering 
    but to leave it open if in a particular implementation the questionnaire is implemented or if the representation towards 
    the user is made (in accordance to the questionnaire definition) by other technical means. In such a case, there would 
    be no QuestionnaireResponse Resource in the bundle because all content is already in concerning resources. In order to 
    handle all FHIR exchange formats equal (as far as sensible), the authors decided to mandate the order placer application 
    with the task.
    </p>
    <p>Applications claiming for conformance with the ORF Implementation Guide shall:
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>Render (and in case of the Questionnaire filler allow for data entry) all elements of a questionnaire in the
        user interface (e.g. on screen, in print). Grouping of items and the order of items within shall be adequately
        reproduced according to the Questionnaire.</li>

        <li>In case of an implementation without Questionnaire and QuestionnaireResponse, the content of otherwise implemented UIs shall 
        be in accordance to the questionnaire definition.</li>
        
        <li>Be able to process all codes related to the generic elements in a Questionnaire.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Vendors of applications with Questionnaire Filler/Questionnaire Receiver Actors are strongly recommended to implement
    interfaces to other applications (such as HIS and PACS) for all data in the generics elements of
    Questionnaires.
    </p>
    <p>Applications designed like this will provide out-of-the-box interconnectivity for generic elements as well as
    out-of-the-box interoperability for all questionnaires as far it concerns user interfaces at filler and receiver
    site.
    </p>
    <p>Nothing speaks against interfaces for data in the use case specific part of a particular Questionnaire. One has
    however to keep in mind, that such interfaces are tied to a specific questionnaire. Ownership or other means, which
    prevent changes of the questionnaire by third parties, are therefore advisable.
    </p>
    <p>The ORF Implementation Guide deals with Transport, Workflow and Content. It is based on FHIR resources and in
    particular the FHIR Questionnaire resource. FHIR specifies RESTful Web services as a mean for transport.&#160; An
    implementation based on RESTful Web services is strongly recommended however not mandatory to comply with the ORF
    Implementation Guide. Workflow is addressed by the scope of ORF Implementation Guide which addresses directional
    information exchange with request and response. Content is defined by a set of generic given elements
    and codes and the possibility to extend both as required by the use cases addressed.
    </p>


    <a name="volume1"></a><h4>ORF Actors, Transactions, and Content Modules</h4>
    <p>This Implementation Guide depends on the <a href="http://www.hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/history.cfml">SDC Implementation Guide</a>:
    </p>
    <p>Questionnaires and forms permeate healthcare. They are used to capture administrative data, claims data, clinical
    information, research information, for public health reporting - every type of data that is manipulated by
    healthcare systems. They provide a user-friendly mechanism for capturing data in a consistent way. In FHIR, forms
    are represented using the Questionnaire resource and completed forms are represented using the QuestionnaireResponse
    resource. The base FHIR specification defines these resources but doesn't provide much guidance around how they
    should be used, nor does it set minimal expectations for interoperation. The <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/">SDC Implementation Guide</a> 
    provides a set of guidance around the use of Questionnaire and QuestionnaireResponse.
    </p>

    <a name="volume1"></a><h5>SDC Specification relevant to CH ORF</h5>
    <p>These sections define the different use-cases supported by SDC, specify the profile(s) needed to meet the use-cases.
    </p>
    <ol>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/search.html">Finding a
            Questionnaire</a> describes expectations for systems serving as form repositories as well as clients who
        will need to search for forms.</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/rendering.html">Advanced
            Rendering</a> describes how to use various questions and the base capabilities of Questionnaire to render
        different types of form elements</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/behavior.html">Form Behavior</a>
        describes how to design 'active' forms that adjust what information is displayed and/or that perform
        calculations based on user input</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/adaptive.html">Adaptive Forms</a>
        describes an architecture to support completing forms where the questionnaire is not pre-defined and instead is
        dynamically developed based on the user's answers</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/populate.html">Questionnaire
            Population</a> describes how to design questionnaires to support pre-population of answers and how to use
        services that support pre-populating forms</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/extraction.html">Data
            Extraction</a> describes how to design questionnaires to support converting completed forms into a FHIR
        resource or Bundle of FHIR resources for subsequent analysis</li>
    </ol>
    <a name="volume1"></a><h5>SDC Actors and workflow relevant to CH ORF</h5>
    <p>To be considered SDC-conformant, a system must adhere to the requirements defined by at least one of these
    statements. Some systems might choose to comply with more than one.
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/sdc-form-designer.html">SDC Form Designer</a>
             - System responsible for creating and editing form designs</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/sdc-form-filler.html">SDC Form Filler</a>
             - System responsible for capturing user form input to produce partially or fully completed forms
        </li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/sdc-form-manager.html">SDC Form Manager</a>
             - Repository for form definitions. May also perform pre-population</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/sdc-form-response-manager.html">SDC Form Response Manager</a>
             - Searchable repository for storage and retrieval of completed and partially completed forms.</li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/sdc-form-receiver.html">SDC Form Receiver</a>
             - Write-only destination to which forms are sent for processing</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The relationship between these roles and a summary of how they can interact is shown in <sup>&#91;Figure 1&#93;</sup>.
    </p>
    <p>
        <div style="max-width:40%;">
            <img src="sdc-form-operations.png" width="472" height="354" />
        </div>
    </p>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Figure 1&#93;</sup>
        <i>SDC Role operations</i>
    </p>

    <a name="volume1"></a><h5>CH ORF</h5>
    <p>This section defines the actors, transactions, and/or content modules specific to this Implementation Guide.
    </p>
    <table>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <th>Actor
                </th>
                <th>Definition
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>A system that renders Questionnaires and allows for filling in. The Questionnaire Filler is also
                responsible for filling in the corresponding resources in the Bundle, corresponds to the 
                <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/sdc-form-filler.html">SDC Form Filler</a>.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>A system that receives a Bundle (according to the Questionnaire) from a Questionnaire filler and
                renders it, corresponds to the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/sdc-form-receiver.html">SDC Form Receiver</a>.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Table 1&#93;</sup>
        <i>Actors in the ORF Implementation Guide</i>
    </p>
    <p>
        <div style="max-width:40%;">
            <img src="ChOrfQuestionnaireHandlingActorDiagram.svg" width="700" height="220"/>
        </div>
    </p>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Figure 2&#93;</sup>
        <i>Questionnaire Handling Actor Diagram</i>
    </p>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Figure 2&#93;</sup>
    shows
    the actors directly involved in the ORF Implementation Guide and the relevant transactions between them. Actors
    which have a mandatory grouping are shown in conjoined boxes.
    </p>
     <table>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <th>Actors
                </th>
                <th>Transactions
                </th>
                <th>Optionality
                </th>
                <th>Reference
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>Submit Bundle [CH ORF-1]
                </td>
                <td>O
                </td>
                <td>3.1
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>Submit Bundle[CH ORF-1]
                </td>
                <td>O
                </td>
                <td>3.1
                </td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Table 2&#93;</sup>
        <i>Actors in the ORF Implementation Guide</i>
    </p>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Table 2&#93;</sup> lists the
    transactions for each actor directly involved in the Order &amp; Referral by Form (ORF) Implementation Guide. To
    claim compliance with this Implementation Guide, an actor shall support all required transactions (labeled “R”)
    and may support the optional transactions (labeled “O”).
    </p>
    <p>The Submit Bundle transaction is marked as optional to allow solutions which choose a different communication
    transaction method like IHE XDS, XDR, XMD to be conform with this Implementation Guide.
    </p>
    <p>A product implementation using this Implementation Guide groups actors from this guide with actors from a workflow or
    transport Implementation Guide to be functional. The grouping of the content module described in this
    Implementation Guide to specific actors is described in more detail in the “Required Actor Groupings” section below.
    </p>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Table 3&#93;</sup> lists the
    content module defined in the Order &amp; Referral by Form (ORF)) Implementation Guide. To claim support with
    this Implementation Guide, an actor shall support all required content modules (labeled “R”) and may support optional
    content modules (labeled “O”). The content module is based on the [Swiss core] profiles.
    </p>
     <table>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <th>Actors
                </th>
                <th>Content Modules
                </th>
                <th>Optionality
                </th>
                <th>Reference
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>ORF Content Module <sup>&#91;Note 1&#93;</sup>
                </td>
                <td>R
                </td>
                <td>Vol 3
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>ORF Content Module <sup>&#91;Note 1&#93;</sup>
                </td>
                <td>R <sup>&#91;Note 1&#93;</sup>
                </td>
                <td>Vol 3
                </td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Table 3&#93;</sup>
        <i>Order &amp; Referral by Form (ORF) Implementation Guide - Actors and Content Modules</i>
    </p>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Note 1&#93;</sup>
        <i>The content of the form depends on the form which itself is defined by the FHIR Questionnaire The FHIR Questionnaire
        defines elements and structure of the form. Codes for coded attributes are provided with a corresponding value set
        (details see ORF Content Module)</i>
    </p>

    <a name="volume1"></a><h5>ORF Actor Descriptions and Actor Requirements</h5>
    <p>Most requirements are documented in Transactions (Volume 2) and Content Modules (Volume 3). This section
    documents any additional requirements on Implementation Guide's actors.
    </p>
    <p>Questionnaire Filler and Questionnaire Receiver Actors may be implemented on a mobile device, although this is
        not
        the primary setting in mind. All other Actors will rather be implemented in a stationary setting because the use
        case addressed involve mostly stationary applications.
    </p>


    <a name="volume1"></a><h4>ORF Actor Options</h4>
    <p>Options that may be selected for each actor in this profile, if any, are listed in <sup>&#91;Table 4&#93;</sup>. 
        Dependencies between options when applicable are specified in notes.
    </p>
     <table>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <th>Actor
                </th>
                <th>Option Name
                </th>
                <th>Reference
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>No options defined
                </td>
                <td>--
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>No options defined
                </td>
                <td>--
                </td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <p><sup>&#91;Table 4&#93;</sup><i>ORF - Actors and Options</i>
    </p>


    <a name="volume1"></a><h4>ORF Required Actor Groupings</h4>
    <p>An Actor from this Implementation Guide (Column 1) shall implement all of the required transactions and/or
        content modules in this profile <i><b>in addition to</b></i> all of the transactions required for the grouped actor
        (Column 2).
    </p>
    <p>If this is a content module, and actors from this Implementation Guide are grouped with actors from a workflow or
        transport profile, the Content Bindings reference column references any specifications for mapping data from the
        content module into data elements from the workflow or transport transactions.
    </p>
    <p>In some cases, required groupings are defined as at least one of an enumerated set of possible actors; this is
        designated by merging column one into a single cell spanning multiple potential grouped actors. Notes are used
        to highlight this situation.
    </p>
    <p>Section 1.5 describes some optional groupings that may be of interest for security considerations and section 1.6
        describes some optional groupings in other related profiles.
    </p>
     <table>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <th>ORF Actor
                </th>
                <th>Actor to be grouped with
                </th>
                <th>Reference
                </th>
                <th>Content Bindings Reference
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>1.1
                </td>
                <td>Volume 3
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>1.1
                </td>
                <td>Volume 3
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>CT Time Client
                </td>
                <td>ITI TF-1: 7.1
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>CT Time Client
                </td>
                <td>ITI TF-1: 7.1
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Table 5&#93;</sup><i>ORF - Required Actor Groupings</i>
    </p>

    <a name="volume1"></a><h4>ORF Overview</h4>
    <a name="volume1"></a><h5>Use Cases</h5>
    <a name="volume1"></a><h6>Questionnaire Usage Process Flow</h6>
    <p>Dr. Miller has a new Patient John Doe who has had an MRI at the radiology service “S-U-P-E-R-XR”. Dr. Miller
        retrieves a special order questionnaire from the SDC Form Manager at S-U-P-E-R-XR which allows ordering of
        images and reports of previous exams. Dr. Miller fills in this questionnaire and sends it back. At S-U-P-E-R-XR, a
        staff member will fill in another Questionnaire with a reply, attaches images and reports an sends all to Dr. Miller.
    </p>

    <a name="volume1"></a><h4>ORF Security Considerations</h4>
    <p>A resource server should not return any patient information unless proper authentication and communications
        security have been proven.
    </p>
    <p>There are many reasonable methods of securing interoperability transactions. These security models can be layered
        in without modifying the characteristics of the ORF Profile transactions. The use of TLS is mandatory.
    </p>
    <p>User authentication on mobile devices is encouraged using Internet User Authorization (IUA) Profile. The network
        communication security and user authentication are layered in at the HTTP transport layer and do not modify the
        interoperability characteristics defined in the ORF Profile.
    </p>
    <p>The Security Audit logging (e.g. ATNA) is recommended. Support for ATNA-based audit logging on the mobile health
        device may be beyond the ability of this constrained environment.
    </p>
    <p>In case vendors decide to include the Patient ID (patient.identifier) as a query parameter on the Resource URL
        (what would be out of the scope of ORF Implementation Guide), this URL pattern would present a risk when using typical
        web server audit logging of URL requests, and browser history. In both of these cases the URL with the patient
        identity would be clearly visible. These risks should be mitigated in system or operational design.
    </p>

    <a name="volume2"></a><h3>Volume 2 – Transactions</h3>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h4>Submit Bundle [CH ORF-1]</h4>
    <p>This section corresponds to Transaction CH ORF-1. Transaction CH ORF-1 is used by the Questionnaire Filler and
        Questionnaire Receiver. This is a combination of extracting resources outlined in the SDC Workflow
        <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/workflow.html">10.1 Optional EHR
            extracts information from Questionnaire Response</a> and sending a Bundle including the extracted
        information according to Volume 3 and Questionnaire Response to the Questionnaire Receiver.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h5>Scope</h5>
    <p>This transaction is used to submit a filled in questionnaire together with required additional resources and
        attachments in a Bundle from a Questionnaire Filler to a Questionnaire Receiver.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h5>Actor Roles</h5>
    <div style="max-width:40%;">
        <img src="ChOrfActorsRoleSubmitBundle.svg" width="620" height="300"/>
    </div>
    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Figure 3&#93;</sup>
        <i>Use Case Diagram</i>
    </p>
     <table>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <th><b>Actor</b>
                </th>
                <th><b>Role</b>
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Filler
                </td>
                <td>A system that allows querying a SDC Form Manager in order to fill in the elements for a
                    Questionnaire
                    Response. Upon completion, a corresponding bundle will be submitted to the Questionnaire Receiver.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Questionnaire Receiver
                </td>
                <td>A system that receives bundles and processes them compliant to the ORF Profile.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <p><sup>&#91;Table 6&#93;</sup><i>Actor Roles</i>
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h5>Referenced Standard</h5>

    <ul>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/index.html">HL7 FHIR</a>
            - Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources
        </li>
        <li>
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/sdc/2019May/index.html">HL7 SDC IG</a>
            - Structured Data Capture Implementation Guide
        </li>
        <li>
            IETF RFC 2616
            - Hypertext Transfer Protocol – HTTP/1.1
        </li>
        <li>
            IETF RFC 7540
            - Hypertext Transfer Protocol – HTTP/2
        </li>
        <li>
            IETF RFC 3986
            - Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax
        </li>
        <li>
            IETF RFC 4627
            - The application/json Media Type for JavaScript Object Notation (JSON)
        </li>
        <li>
            IETF RFC 6585
            - Additional HTTP Status Codes
        </li>
        <li>
            <a href="https://www.ihe.net/uploadedFiles/Documents/ITI/IHE_ITI_Suppl_Appx-Z.pdf">IHE Appendix on HL7 FHIR</a>
            - Appendix Z – FHIR Implementation Material (Trial Implementation)
        </li>
    </ul>

    <a name="volume2"></a><h5>Interaction Diagram</h5>
    <p>
        <div style="max-width:40%;">
            <img src="ChOrfInteractionDiagramSubmitBundle.svg" width="400" height="210"/>
        </div>
    </p>
    <p><sup>&#91;Figure 4&#93;</sup>
        <i>Interaction Diagram</i>
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h6>Submit Bundle</h6>
    <p>The transaction uses the HTTP POST method on the target Questionnaire Receiver endpoint to convey the
        questionnaire
        bundle as a FHIR transaction.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h7>Trigger Events</h7>
    <p>After the Questionnaire is completed by the Questionnaire filler user, the Questionnaire Filler submits the
        corresponding bundle to the Questionnaire receiver.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h7>Message Semantics</h7>
    <p>The Questionnaire Filler shall initiate a FHIR “transaction” using a “create” action by sending an HTTP POST
        request method composed of a FHIR Bundle Resource containing the Composition resource and all resources referenced in,
        in particular one Questionnaire Resource, one QuestionnaireResponse Resource and additional resources according to
        the Questionnaire Profile.
    </p>
    <p>The media type of the HTTP body shall be either <code>“application/json+fhir”</code> or
        <code>“application/xml+fhir”</code>.
    </p>
    <p>See <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/http.html#transaction">http://hl7.org/fhir/http.html#transaction</a> for complete
        requirements of a transaction. See <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/bundle-transaction.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/bundle-transaction.html</a> for
        example of a transaction bundle.
    </p>
    <p>Submit Bundle is sent to the base URI as defined in FHIR. See <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/http.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/http.html</a> for the definition of “http”
        access methods and “base”.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h8>Bundle Resources</h8>
    <p>For complete information on constructing a FHIR Bundle Resource, see: <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/bundle.html">http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/bundle.html</a>
    </p>
    <p>The FHIR <code>Bundle.meta.profile</code> shall include the value
        <code><a href="http://fhir.ch/ig/ch-orf/StructureDefinition/ch-orf-document">http://fhir.ch/ig/ch-orf/StructureDefinition/ch-orf-document</a></code>.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h7>Expected Actions</h7>
    <p>The Questionnaire Receiver shall accept both media types <code>application/json+fhir</code> and
        <code>application/xml+fhir</code>.
    </p>
    <p>On receipt of the submission, the Questionnaire Receiver shall validate the resources and respond with one of the
        HTTP codes defined in Section 3.4.4.2.2 Message Semantics.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h6>Status Message</h6>
    <p>The Questionnaire receiver returns a HTTP Status code appropriate to the processing, conforming to the
        transaction specification requirements as specified in 
        <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/http.html#transaction">http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/http.html#transaction</a>
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h7>Trigger Events</h7>
    <p>This message shall be sent once the questionnaire bundle is received and completely processed.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h7>Message Semantics</h7>
    <p>When the Questionnaire Receiver has successfully processed the POST transaction, then the Questionnaire Receiver
        shall return an HTTP response with an overall status code.
    </p>
    <p>In order to allow the Questionnaire Filler to know the outcomes of processing the transaction, and the identities
        assigned to the resources by the Questionnaire Receiver, the Questionnaire Receiver shall return a Bundle, with
        type set to transaction-response, that contains one entry for each entry in the request, in the same order, with the
        outcome of processing the entry. See FHIR <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/bundle.html#transaction-response">http://hl7.org/fhir/r4/bundle.html#transaction-response</a>
    </p>
    <p>Each entry element shall contain a response element which details the outcome of processing the entry - the HTTP
        status code. All other elements are not required.
    </p>
    <p>On success, the Questionnaire Receiver shall return the HTTP status code 200 – OK.
    </p>
    <p>Guidance on handling Access Denied related to use of 403 and 404 can be found in IHE Appendix on HL7 FHIR Z.7.
    </p>
    <p>On failure, the Questionnaire Receiver shall return the HTTP status codes as follows:
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>400 Bad Request - resource could not be parsed or failed basic FHIR validation rules like reference
            inconsistencies, schema violations, etc.</li>
        <li>404 Not Found - resource type not supported.</li>
        <li>422 Unprocessable Entity - one or more proposed resources violated applicable FHIR profiles or server
            business rules.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>In addition, the Questionnaire Receiver may also send 5xx HTTP status codes to indicate non-transaction related
        failures. Note that the Questionnaire Filler may also encounter non-FHIR endpoints which will not return a Bundle in the response.
    </p>
    <p>The Questionnaire Receiver may return HTTP redirect responses (responses with HTTP status codes 301, 302, 303 or
        307) in response to a request.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h7>Expected Actions</h7>
    <p>If the Questionnaire Receiver returns an HTTP redirect response (HTTP status codes 301, 302, 303, or 307), the
        Questionnaire Filler shall follow that redirection, although it may stop processing if it detects a loop.
    </p>
    <p>The Questionnaire Receiver processes the results according to application-defined rules.
    </p>
    <p>If a Questionnaire Receiver cannot automatically recover from an error condition, at a minimum, it should display
        the error to the user.
    </p>
    <a name="volume2"></a><h6>Conformance Resource</h6>
    <p>Questionnaire Receiver implementing this transaction should provide a Conformance Resource as described in IHE
        Appendix on HL7 FHIR Z.3 indicating the operation has been implemented.
    </p>

    <a name="volume3"></a><h3>Volume 3 – Content Modules</h3>

    <a name="volume3"></a><h4>Questionnaire Content</h4>
    <p>This section describes the content of a form. The following definitions apply:
    </p>
    <p>Request and responses consist of filled in questionnaires. Some elements of the questionnaire are generic given
        elements (such as author, data entry person, receiver etc.) and are always present in a questionnaire compliant to
        the ORF Implementation Guide. In addition, a questionnaire will contain elements which are use case specific. The
        ORF Implementation Guide makes no assumptions about the nature of such elements: structure and content (including
        coding of codes elements) are in the responsibility of those creating a form for a particular use case.
    </p>
    <p>As this Implementation Guide is based on FHIR, the following rules apply:
    </p>
    <p>Items, grouping of items, order of groups and order of elements within groups of a questionnaire shall be defined
        in a Questionnaire Resource. The Questionnaire Resource is defined by means of the SDC From Designer and made
        available by the SDC Form Manager.
    </p>
    <p>Based on the Questionnaire, a Questionnaire Filler defines a QuestionnaireResponse and appropriate additional
        resources aimed at transmitting the information provided by the Questionnaire filler in a standardized
        structured form. Upon completion of the questionnaire, the Questionnaire Filler shall create a bundle with all resources
        mentioned above.
    </p>
    <p>Questionnaires may be accompanied by additional material which can be attached or sent by postal mail (e.g.
        xray-films or paper documents). The use case may require some references between attached objects (e.g. which
        pdf-reports belongs to which imaging study).
    </p>


    <a name="volume3"></a><h4>Generic elements of a questionnaire</h4>
    <p>A questionnaire shall have a set of generic elements (e.g. author, data entry person, receiver etc.). 
        <sup>&#91;Table 7&#93;</sup> lists the generic given elements.
    </p>
     <table>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <th><b>Name</b>
                </th>
                <th colspan="2"><b>Role taker</b>
                </th>
                <th><b>HL7 V3<br /> Equivalent</b>
                </th>
                <th><b>FHIR<br /> Representation</b>
                </th>
                <th><b>Comment</b>
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <th>
                </th>
                <th><b>Human</b>
                </th>
                <th><b>Organization</b>
                </th>
                <th>
                </th>
                <th>
                </th>
                <th>
                </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Author
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>Author
                </td>
                <td>PractitionerRole
                </td>
                <td>The person/organization responsible for the form content.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Data Entry Person
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>DataEnterer
                </td>
                <td>PractitionerRole
                </td>
                <td>The person/organization who has typed/filled in the form content.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Urgent Notification Contact for this document
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>PrimaryInformationRecipient
                </td>
                <td>PractitionerRole
                </td>
                <td>An information recipient to notify for urgent matters (e.g. in a radiology service, the radiologist 
                    has to be called by phone right away at the time the document is received.)
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Urgent Notification Contact for the Response to this document
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>PrimaryInformationRecipient
                </td>
                <td>PractitionerRole
                </td>
                <td>
                    <p>An information recipient to notify for urgent matters about the response (e.g. in a clinical
                        setting, the referring doctor has to be called by phone right away at the time the images and
                        reports arrive).
                    </p>
                    <p>The Urgent Notification Contact for the Response can be specified already in the request. At the
                        time the response is written, this element shall be populated to the Urgent Notification Contact
                        element in the response.
                    </p>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Receiver
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>PractitionerRole
                </td>
                <td>Person/organization who receives the document.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Copy Receiver
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>Patient/Organization
                </td>
                <td>Person/organization who receives the copy of this order (shall receive also all results therefrom).
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Patient
                </td>
                <td>X
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>Patient
                </td>
                <td>The principle target of a particular form content is one patient (for obstetrical and neonatal use
                    cases see...).
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Precedent Document Identifier
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>This element provides a link to the preceding document (Bundle.identifier) in a thread (e.g. from a response to the
                    request). 
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Date
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>Date, the document was created.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Priority
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
                <td>na
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>
                </td>
                <td>Order priority.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <p><sup>&#91;Table 7&#93;</sup> <i>Generic elements in Questionnaires compliant to the ORF Implementation Guide</i>
    </p>

    <p>
        <sup>&#91;Table 7&#93;</sup> shows that the FHIR representation of elements representing a person and/or an organisation 
        is defined by the <b>PractitionerRole</b> resource. The Practitioner and/or the Organisation resource can then be referenced 
        from the PractitionerRole resource.
    </p>

    <a name="volume3"></a><h4>Healthcare domain specific elements of a questionnaire</h4>
     
        <a name="volume3"></a><h5>ServiceRequest resource</h5>

        <p>
            The CH ORF context specific requirements for this resource are shown in the profile 
            <a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-servicerequest.html">CH ORF ServiceRequest</a>.
        </p>

        <a name="volume3"></a><h5>DocumentReference resource</h5>
        <p>There may be the need to provide a linkage between particular files or between a particular file and an imaging
        study (e.g. a link between a PDF-File containing a report and a DICOM study). Such links shall be expressed with
        a DocumentReference resource.
        </p>

        <p>
            The CH ORF context specific requirements for this resource are shown in the profile 
            <a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-documentreference.html">CH ORF DocumentReference</a>.
        </p>
        

    <a name="volume3"></a><h4>FHIR Representation</h4>
    <p>FHIR depicts forms (questionnaires) in a Questionnaire Resource. A Questionnaire Resource can be conceived as an
        empty questionnaire where as the filled in questionnaire refers to the QuestionnaireResponse Resource.
        QuestionnaireResponse Resources are certainly structured but due to their flexibility in design not in a
        standardized manner. FHIR addresses this issue by means of its standardized resources.
    </p>
    <p>The Order &amp; Referral by Form Implementation Guide is based on two FHIR Resources profiles. For details on
        profiling FHIR see HL7 FHIR <a href="http://www.hl7.org/fhir/profiling.html">http://www.hl7.org/fhir/profiling.html</a>. For details on
        FHIR resources and data-types see HL7 FHIR <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/">http://hl7.org/fhir/</a>.
    </p>
    <ol>
        <li>The Order &amp; Referral by Form Questionnaire (ORF) Implementation Guide defines the usage of the FHIR
            Questionnaire Resource within the Order &amp; Referral by Form. The Questionnaire Resource is an organized
            collection of questions intended to solicit information from patients, providers or other individuals
            involved in the healthcare domain. They may be simple flat lists of questions or can be hierarchically organized in
            groups and sub-groups, each containing questions. The Questionnaire defines the questions to be asked, how
            they are ordered and grouped and what the constraints are on the allowed answers. The results of a Questionnaire
            can be communicated using the QuestionnaireResponse resource (see 
            <a href="http://www.hl7.org/fhir/questionnaire.html">http://www.hl7.org/fhir/questionnaire.html</a>).</li>
        <li>The Order &amp; Referral by Form Document (ORF) Profile defines the usage of the FHIR Bundle within the
            Order &amp; Referral by Form (ORF) Implementation Guide. The ORFDocumentProfile consist of a FHIR document
            (bundle) that contains the results of a filled in Questionnaire (QuestionnaireResponse Resource) together with the
            structured resources which map all information filled in the questionnaire. The 
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/bundle.html">Bundle</a> is of 
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/bundle-definitions.html#Bundle.type">type</a> &quot;document&quot; and has a 
            <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/composition.html">Composition</a> resource as the first resource in the
            bundle, followed by a series of other resources, referenced from the Composition resource. The bundle gathers all
            the content of the document into a single document which may be signed and managed as required. The
            resources include both human readable and computer processable sections. In addition, a bundle as defined in this
            profile shall include a CSS stylesheets and optionally it may include a signature.<br /><br />Any resource
            referenced directly in the Composition Resource shall be included in the bundle. Other resources that these referenced
            resources refer to shall also be included in the bundle. Including these additional resources will make the
            document bigger, but will save applications from needing to retrieve the linked resources.</li>
    </ol>
    <a name="volume3"></a><h5>FHIR Resources Constraints</h5>
    <p>This section lists FHIR resources for which these <a href="profiles.html">CH ORF profiles</a> provide additional information. Resources not listed here
        follow the specifications of FHIR. For details refer to 
        <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/resourcelist.html">https://www.hl7.org/fhir/resourcelist.html</a>.
    </p>

    <a name="volume3"></a><h6>Composition resource</h6>

    <p>
        The CH ORF context specific requirements for this resource are shown in the profile 
        <a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-composition.html">CH ORF Composition</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
        In the Composition, general information about the document is defined, such as title, type and category. 
        In the CH ORF exchange format, no fixed values are determined for these elements, only a preferred binding to specific ValueSets is made. 
        These values are context-dependent and have to be specified in the corresponding derived exchange format.
        They must be defined as fixedValues or limited ValueSet in the Composition profile.
        <table>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <th><b>Element</b></th>
                    <th><b>Description</b></th>
                    <th><b>DataType</b></th>
                    <th><b>ValueSet</b></th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-composition.html#Composition.title">Composition.title</a></td>
                    <td>Meaningful human-readable title of the document</td>
                    <td><code>string</code></td>
                    <td>-</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-composition.html#Composition.type">Composition.type</a></td>
                    <td>Precise type of the document</td>
                    <td><code>CodeableConcept</code></td>
                    <td><a href="http://fhir.ch/ig/ch-epr-term/ValueSet-DocumentEntry.typeCode.html">DocumentEntry.typeCode</a></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-composition.html#Composition.category">Composition.category</a></td>
                    <td>High-level kind of the document at a macro level</td>
                    <td><code>CodeableConcept</code></td>
                    <td><a href="http://fhir.ch/ig/ch-epr-term/ValueSet-DocumentEntry.classCode.html">DocumentEntry.classCode</a></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
        <p>
            <sup>&#91;Table 8&#93;</sup> <i>Generel information about the document defined in Composition</i>
        </p>
    </p>

    <a name="volume3"></a><h6>Questionnaire resource</h6>
    <p>The intention of the ORF Implementation Guide is to provide a standardized representation of forms at sender and
    receiver site as well. This is achieved with the Questionnaire Resource, which defines representation of all
    elements for the user (with the help of a CSS) and user interaction as well (e.g. with drop down lists).
    </p>
    <p>This approach requires two things:
    </p>
    <ol>
        <li>Precise definition of all questions</li>
        <li>Mapping between elements of the Questionnaire Resource and the corresponding elements of the other resources
            in the bundle</li>
    </ol>
    <p>Both is achieved by assigning meaningful concepts to all elements concerned. For codes refer to Appendix A.
    </p>

    <p>
        The CH ORF context specific requirements for this resource are shown in the profile 
        <a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-questionnaire.html">CH ORF Questionnaire</a>.
    </p>
     
    <a name="volume3"></a><h6>QuestionnaireResponse resource</h6>
    <p>The QuestionnaireResponse Resource depends of the definition of the Questionnaire Resource and is therefore use
        case specific. For deriving QuestionnaireResponse Resources from the Questionnaire Resources refer to 
        <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/r4/questionnaireresponse.html">https://www.hl7.org/fhir/r4/questionnaireresponse.html</a>.
    </p>

    <p>
        The CH ORF context specific requirements for this resource are shown in the profile 
        <a href="StructureDefinition-ch-orf-questionnaireresponse.html">CH ORF QuestionnaireResponse</a>.
    </p>
</div>